hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today in Spring boot I
will be covering hatos restful apis yeah
weird name right and even if you see its
full form like its full form says that
hyper media as the engine of application
State Mo here right so before we start
if you search over the internet and you
will see that hey is it still popular
you will see many feedback which says
that nowadays companies are not using it
it has so many disadvantage don't use it
but I would say that hey guys welcome to
reality hatos is being used in very big
product companies today
also right and I will not only tell you
what how not to use it but also tell how
to use it what advantage it adds it
tells the client what the next action
you can perform after a particular
step let
understand this with this
example so here in this simple example
let's say that I have reached to this
step using a post API SL add user I am
able to add a user but with currently
it's
unverified now what's the next step I
can do the next step I after adding a
user I can do is I can make a get call
and get the details of this user I can
even delete this that also I can do or I
can even verify this user right so
verify again has different ways so you
can say that after verifying uh there
are different ways to verify one is
through SMS so when I say that SMS
verify start let's say that you get some
PIN code and which you might have to
enter through which you will finish it
so different API for start different API
for finish similarly for email verify
start where you will get a email has
been sent to user that hey this is the
code now you have to push it somewhere
so you will actually finishing your
email
verify so this is a small use case which
I have come up with and I will tell you
why it is important to understand when
we will see when not to use and when to
use it
but you got it right when I say that it
tells the client what's the next action
you can perform after particular step so
this is one step and what is the next
action after adding a user either you
can do a get call either you can delete
it or either you can verify it these are
the next action you can do okay and we
will see uh more details but let's see
that how the response looks like so now
let's say that I am using a post API to
add a user
now the response of it if you are not
using a heos link how it going to look
like so this is the response you will
get when you add a particular user you
got a user ID okay this ID is
representing a unique ID in your DB
through which you can fet the details so
we return a user ID and let's say name
and currently what is the verified
status let's say it's unverified
but what if I want to use heos Link heos
restful API so in this case with heos
link this is how the response generally
looks
like we send the user ID same name
verify status unverified but see this
is so links inside links we send what
all the next step you can do so it's an
array so it's an array you can even have
more like this so all the actions which
can be
done after this current state what all
the next things you can do you can put
it into the links so here I have just
for example I have added one link where
it says that relation is
self the URI and what is the type so
this is nothing but a HTTP method for
this URI whether it's a get call Post
call patch call delete call so we can
add that URI is the what is the next URI
can be
invoked right and what is the relation
of this
API with this current
state okay so currently I put self means
this API will return you the details of
this only it's generally a get call self
is always def facto you can say that
even if I don't write get right and if
it is relation is self it's a def facto
it's like a get call for this one if you
have to F the details of this user ID
generally self represent that only that
it's a get call
okay but still we will see more details
about it but for now what I wanted to
show you without hatos link generally
what how the response look like and with
hatos
how the response generally looks like so
this is what
actually important here we
provide what all the next action can be
taken after this
step how to do that I will tell
you but before understanding how to do
this let's understand when to use and
why to use hatos Lang very important
right so the are two major purpose of
using hatos link right and the two major
purpose we want to use heos is to
achieve loose coupling and API
Discovery so when I say that loose
coupling is loose coupling
between your
client and
server
application and when I say that API
Discovery what I mean is that let's say
at server there are hundreds of
apis so client should not have like
difficult time to understand like okay
uh where this API going to be used where
this API going to be used what should be
the API for this so in the links itself
you are getting your uh API showed that
hey invoke this API you can invoke this
API after this one
you can invoke all this this API after
this okay so that's what I mean here API
Discovery even though client not need to
have like okay what all the different
apis are available server here tell me
no it's not required even server in the
links itself can tell these are the five
apis now eligible after this particular
step now client can use
those now to achieve above server
provide the next set of API action in
the response itself right which client
can take so that client have less
business logic around apis which API to
invoke when to invoke how to
invoke but
remember adding all the next set of
action can make our API response blow up
and has several disadvantage before
telling you the disadvantage let see
this response now let's say that I
showed you this example right now let's
say that when the user has been added
through post API this/ add user now in
the response I am sending the
next actions link what can be performed
so I can do get call delete call verify
call something something something now
if I add all the links like this so
after post let's say
post add user
call now if my response looks like this
hey in the link I am providing hey you
can invoke get call you can invoke
delete so type I have put delete this is
the API URI and the relation I have put
is that hey this the relation of this
API after the this next step is to
remove it okay so I have put remove then
you can also update it so for example I
have just put hey you can use this API
it's a patch and relation is you
updation you can do verify you can
either you can do verify start or verify
finished depend because still verify is
not finished it is still in unverified
so both are eligible verify start is
also an eligible operation verify finish
is also an eligible operation because
currently status is
unverified so now here if you see one
thing if we keep on adding next set of
operation this is just a very basic use
case I have taken and now here if you
see 1 2 3 for five links I have added
now in a big Industries after a
particular step there are so many things
is possible if you keep on adding all
the next set of operations
it going to bloat your API
response right and that's where
everywhere we say that never use it
never use it because if you use it
heavily if you keep on putting the next
set of action
ultimately not recommended at all right
why because it will increase the
complexity as server side why it will
increase the complexity of server side
because see all this links are Dynamic
it's not static links based upon the
current state I am
determining what
all what all steps are applicable so I'm
creating those links dynamically right
for you might be some other idid getting
created for me some other ID getting
created so it's all Dynamic so at if you
are at step one this three actions is
getting into the link if you are at a
step two only these two links are
getting created so these are dynamically
at server side so means you are
increasing the complexity at server side
and also when you are adding this uh
business logic you are increasing the
payload size also and ultimately it
nothing it will impact your latency
too so never ever add all the possible
next set of action just like that never
ever do that hey this this is all 10 20
actions are possible do that no so now
you can ask me right hey if I if I can't
add all next set of action then what
next set of action I can
add I'll tell you but with this example
first let's see this go back to
again so we have to do proper analysis
need to be done what actually will help
us to achieve lose
coupling now see this diagram
again
so just in one minute I will walk you
through this diagram again what I'm
trying to achieve so I have added a user
through post API which user is in
currently unverified State you can do a
get call you can do delete it and even
you can verify for verify you can do
through SMS or through email and in both
the way you first have to do this a API
start SMS verify start and then SMI
verify
finish email email verify start email
verify finish okay after this your user
will get verified but let's say this is
the diagram which I have done so now
let's understand
this so here if you see
that let's forget that we are not using
heos let's say that we are not using
heos for a moment let's say we are not
using it so how your response going to
look like after this
post add
user call how your response going to
look like so you are adding a user
ID your
name what is the current uh verify
status it is
unverified okay but also let's say that
the server also Al do has the knowledge
that okay for this
country verify type should be SMS so
that uh client should initiate a SMS
verify
start So currently verify type is SMS
and verify state is currently not yet
started SMS is not yet started so means
it has to first start if it is already
started means you can only do finish now
so this is a very basic response let's
say that the server is sending to the
client currently user is
unverified user can verify using type
SMS and currently the verify state is
not yet
started so now see what the client logic
look like see I not a uh client side uh
engineer so definitely this code is not
uh valid for client but the logic should
be I think the same if the client has to
code this way so what client will should
do to get user
verified so client will check this
response hey if verify status is
unverified yes it is reading from the
response unverified go to the next step
what is the verified type if it is SMS
or email if it okay it is SMS go inside
this does verify status has been started
oh it's
not yet started if it is not yet started
means I have to call this API SMS verify
start if the verify state is let's say
started then I have to invoke SMS verify
finish
API and if it is an email the same thing
if verify state is not yet started I
have to
call this API email verify start if
verify state is started I have to call
email verify finish so now here if you
see this generally the client code
should be present to initiate a
verify for the
user now I see that there is a lot tight
coupling between clients and server
client needs some info before it can
decide which a API verify API to invoke
now client here if you see lot of
business logic why client has this
business logic here if it is unverified
whether through SMS or email if SMS
whether it has been started or not
started if not started invoke this API
if it started invoke this
API so this is I call it very tight
coupling and this is just a one use case
if there are 100 of use case imagine the
client code now let's say that heos
comes into the
picture I can make this typ couple code
into a loose couple through heos link
now let's say that this is the response
I will send what is the user
ID name verify status unverified but now
here if you see that I am not sending
sms or not yet started at server side
itself I will compute all this thing and
in the link I will just simply provide
hey this is the next you should do you
you can do this is the URI this is the
post call and the relation is that uh
this is a verify link you can do verify
so here if you see I am just telling
invoke this API SMS verify finish now
internally server itself has determined
that okay it is unverified and I have
already started I started the SMS
verification so next can be done is
finish
only okay so I have just provided the
next link only this one I haven't
doesn't provided all the links only this
now how the client code going to look
like if verify status is unverified yes
it is
unverified use the link which is given
in the heos just use this link and and
invoke just invoke
it now client doesn't need to know
whether I can uh do it through SMS or
email whether SMS is started or not
started if it is already started I need
to invoke this finish all this logic is
now goes to the server right now here if
you see that client is now we can say
that the client and service is Loosely
coupled and all this logic right this is
actually business logic this should be
present at server like what's the next
thing is
eligible so you got it when to use it
how how with this
example we have from a tight couple
between client and server how we have
achieved the loose
coupling so this is how I believe it
should be hatos Ling should be used we
should not put unnecessarily the next
links otherwise it going to be difficult
hell to manage this API so very
cautiously we have to add a link yes if
you don't add it there would be a tight
coupl if we add it yes we are achieving
loose coupling okay so this is one
example if you understand it now I will
tell you how we can add this
link so one thing is we have to add a
dependency so this is in the dependency
you have to put into the pal a do spring
spring framework. boot spring boot
starter heos and whatever the latest
version you can use it okay so now here
if you see this is the rest controller
and this is the post add user call so
whenever uh user is getting added this
API will get involved so here I just
getting a response just see that this
user response has all this things user
ID name verify State this thing itself
user ID name verify State and for links
what I have done
is I have created a new class hatos
links and in that I have put the list of
Link okay and I have provided one add
link where the link can be added so this
link right this link object it is coming
from that spring boot the dependency
which we have added so this dependency
this link object is
coming so why I have uh so why in this I
haven't added that list of Link because
see we could have 20 50 apis and in 50
apis we might have to add a hatos link
so we can't uh so it's better that we
create one class in that we put a list
of link and in the response whichever
required it can extend it automatically
add link this links will be also part of
this
one okay so now when the AP got invoked
now let's say that user. get user uh or
you can say that instead of get user
let's say that add user would happen and
this is the response you
got okay now in this response already
this fields are filled up user ID name
and verify status now we have we have to
add the links so here how to add a
link so there are two ways I will tell
you the one way is through web MVC link
Builder so what we can do is uh do link
to user controller. class this
class slash what is the next
next
URI right so user controller class what
it will do is let's say this class is/
API slash so that would be
used so slash API SL would get
added then this
method SMS hyen verify hyphen finish
this get
added
slash the dynamic user id/ let's say 1 2
3 4 5 6 this from this user us response
I am reading this user
ID what is the relation it's the URI
which I am adding it is to verify so
this is the relation it's a verify link
and it is a post type the same
which ultimately it's going to be show
like
this right and you can add into your
response response. addlink add this link
so this is the user response right and
this since this is a child of this hatos
link you can call add link also and this
one link get added if you have to add
more link you can keep on adding more
link do add link one more you can create
you can add it but I would always say
you that add
cautiously so this is one way to add and
another way to add is like link off this
link object is the same the dependency
which we have added link. off and you
can provide the UR itself whatever the/
API SL this this is all a string you
have made a
URI then what is the relation and what
is the with type and you can add this
link so both the ways whichever you find
it's easy and uh either through slash
slash or either directly simply in one
string we can add it in to our
response okay and this is how it going
to get added so it's an array we have
added as an array list right so it's an
array and we have added only one link
which is verify relation type is post
and this is the verify
link okay so this is based on our
business logic based on business logic
we
determine what UI to add it's not a
static so I hope this heos is
clear if there is an argument comes that
why you are using it what advantage heos
you're going to add loose coupling is
the big advantage and maybe you can come
up with your own example but this is the
example which I come up with where
through
verify I have showed you how the tight
coupling looks
like and how we can achieve the loose
coupling with the hatos Ling but if you
have more doubts let's discuss in the
comment section and but I hope this
video would be uh useful but this is
this topic is generally known as hatos
restful
apis okay guys thank you bye